Stanford
University. All right. The last time I
started to set up a little bit of
mathematics, some very elementary
mathematics, but let me just review it
and then we'll use it. The purpose of
using it today is going to be to get to
the Boltzmon distribution. The Boltzmon
distribution is the probability
distribution that a system in thermal
equilibrium with a heat bath. Remember
what thermal equilibrium means? It means
that the small system is in contact with
a large heat bath. When we focus on that
small system, energy goes back and
forth. There are fluctuations in the
energy uh over time scales which are
sufficiently long and not very long for
most systems. The energy will have some
average value in the subsystem but it
will also fluctuate some and so there
will be a probability distribution. That
probability distribution is the special
probability distribution associated with
thermal
equilibrium and we want to try to find
out something about it.
In fact, it happens to have a rather
universal
form which is called the Boltzman
distribution. Sometimes Maxwell Boltzman
distribution, but it was really Boltzman
who really got it right. So let's begin
with the
idea instead of a heat bath of arbitrary
kind, it turns out to be simplest. This
is a mathematical convenience. This is
not uh this is not deep fundamental
point. We could take the heat bath to be
anything. But it turns out to be
simplest if we're interested in a system
that we will call
a thing about the system is we want it
to have a lot of degrees of freedom in
terms of molecules. We wanted to have a
lot of them. That's a system. It has a
collection of of level a collection of
states. Let's uh let's put an axis over
here to represent the states of the
system. And the little tick marks here
could represent the energy levels, the
possible energy
levels. If the energy is continuous, if
it's a continuous variable, as it really
is in classical mechanics, we'll have to
take that into account. But for the
moment, let's just simplify things and
say this a discrete collection of states
which we label with an
I. The lowest one is called the ground
state, the state of lowest energy. And
up we go. Then in most systems of
interest, there's no ceiling to the uh
to the energy levels. They go up and up
and up. So there's an infinite number of
energy levels.
And in place of a heat bath, well not in
place of a heat bath, but a special case
of a heat bath which this is
particularly interest easy to analyze.
We just imagine a bunch of copies of the
same
system. Why make things more complicated
than just repeating the same system over
and over again? No particular reason.
And as I said, that does make things
easier.
Now in order that A comes to thermal
equilibrium of course in in the heat
bath of all the other replicas or copies
of A it's necessary that heat can be
exchanged or that energy can be
exchanged between them. And that for
example could happen oh in a variety of
ways. Possibly molecules go back and
forth through a permeable partition.
um other ways radiation could go back
and forth. Whatever the way the energy
goes back and forth, let's just uh
indicate it by drawing little pipes
connecting uh the
uh all of the copies
together and we'll say that there are n
copies. n is a very big number and in
the end we'll really be interested in
what happens when n goes to
infinity. Now let's focus on a set of
numbers which we can call occupation
numbers. Now the if if you've heard of
occupation numbers before in particular
in the context of quantum field theory
don't confuse it. Uh this this is a
different concept. Uh the question is
how many of these
boxes occupy a particular energy level
I? So to represent this we could draw
some lines. Uh the lines could indicate
the first box
here is in
state 1 2 3 4 5 I = 5. The second one
and of course this changes with time.
they rearrange. But at a given
instant, we could imagine drawing lines
and those lines would simply tell us
this box is in this state, this box is
in this state. Now, of course, you can
have several boxes all in the same
state. No reason why there can't be two
boxes in the same state or three or four
or five. And so we can define a
collection of
integers the number of copies. Let's
call it a little
n. Little n is the number of
copies drawn from big n which occupy the
state
i. I'm not sure that uh that the copies
occupy the state or the state occupies
the copy but uh you know what I mean.
So that's N I and of course most of them
are zero. Most of them are zero. The NI
is because there's an infinite number of
states but only a finite number of
boxes. And besides I'm going to also
assume that the total energy of the
whole collection is fixed. Let's call it
E
total. And I might as well now not even
define E total. There's an average
energy that each box has. Since they're
all identical to each other, when they
come to thermal equilibrium, they will
all have the same average energy just by
symmetry. Okay? So, they'll all have the
same average energy. And of course, the
total energy, which is fixed, frozen,
will simply be in times the average
energy. Let's write it down. D
total is of course N times the average
energy in each
box. I'm not going to always indicate
that I mean
averages. I've gotten tired of using the
symbol like that. It takes it takes too
much space. I will sometimes use the
over bar and sometimes I'll just ignore
it. Please ask me if you're confused
about whether I'm talking about averages
or not.
uh but since the total energy is fixed
it must be n * the average energy of any
given box. So this is one
fact. What other facts do we have?
Well first of all each energy level has
a certain uh a certain value. These ins
are subject to two constraints and
really only two constraints. Things
fluctuate. Energy goes back and forth.
Things change with time but certain
things don't change. First of all, the
number of boxes doesn't
change by assumption by uh that's our
system, a fixed number of boxes. This is
the number of boxes in the i state. And
so it must be the
case that the sum of i of n sub i that
must equal the total number of boxes.
the number of boxes in the first state
plus the number of boxes in the second
state and so forth and so on must all
together add up to n and obviously since
n is bounded and can't get to since n is
big sorry since n is bounded none of
these n subis can be bigger than n and
that means most of the states must be
unoccupied most of the n's must be zero
most of the little ns must be zero but
that's okay nevertheless
uh first statement. Next
statement, if we take the number of
boxes in the state I times the energy of
the I state, that gives us the total
energy. Sum over I sum
over let's be very clear now this sum is
not the sum over the boxes. It's the sum
over the energy
levels. The number of boxes in the state
I. So I labels states not boxes. So
don't get confused by that. Second, the
number of boxes with each energy level
when added up has to add up to the total
energy. So that must add up to either e
total depending on the way we want to
write it.
But we can also remember that that
happens to be n times the average energy
of any given
box. The
energy total energy and the total number
of boxes are fixed and frozen and will
never change in this discussion. And so
these can be thought of as
constraints. Whatever we do, we will not
change these things. Now the next
question is how many ways are
there given a set of occupation
numbers given a set of occupation
numbers how many ways are
there that those occupation numbers can
be realized let me just give you a
simple example
supposing there are a bunch of states
and only two boxes
is and uh let me take the case
uh
n1 that's the ground state is equal to
one and n2 is equal to one. How many
ways are there that n1 can equal one and
n2 equal one just one way both boxes
have
uh are in the first state. So we would
represent that by drawing a line like
that. The line this
point on the other hand what's the uh
just to illustrate the concept. What's
the number of ways that n1 can be
zero? What I want
wasn't that
n2= n1= 2. Yeah. N1= 2. N2 is zero. And
n2 is equal to zero.
That's the number of ways.
It's also one, isn't it?
The first one
was this is correct. Correct. This is
correct for what you Sorry, I thought I
right for what I drew. N1 is two and N2
is zero. Okay.
Right. Okay. How many ways are there of
making n1 equal to two? One. One way.
Okay. In general, there may be many ways
of doing it for many ways of having a
given set of occupation numbers. For
example, we could have n1 equal one.
Let's see. And uh sum has to be two. Sum
has to add up to two. And what's
what's another possibility? Uh yeah, one
go to one. Yeah, one go to one, the
other go to two, right? So n1 is one
and two is one,
right? Now you want to go to right. So
now we
have
either this
situation or what's the other situation
was drawing
just the reverse not the reverse the uh
inverse the first
box goes to the lowest energy level and
the second box goes uh just cross them
over. All right. So there are two ways
to have n1= 1 and n2=2. In general there
will be a multiplicity of ways of
obtaining a given set of occupation
numbers. What is that multiplicity? What
is the
multiplicity in
general? I told you what the answer was
last time. I assume you've all worked it
out. It's not very hard. It's a simple
combinator uh problem. Standard uh uh
combinatoric problem. And I'm not going
to prove it here. Uh we'll just write
down the answer. Let's call that number
I just call it number. the number of
ways that the energy can be partitioned
up among the boxes such that we have a
given set of n
subs and that is
equal to n
factorial divided by n1 factorial n2
factorial n3 factorial dot dot dot.
In other words, let's write it as n
factorial over the product over i the
product over all the states of the
occupation
number n sub i
factorial. That's the answer to that
combinatorial problem.
Now let me tell you first of all that in
a practical
applications these kind of things think
of them as functions of the ns. First of
all all the ns in the problem are going
to be very
large. Capital n is a huge huge number
of copies.
so huge that the occupation numbers of
every state will also be assumed to be
large. Now, of course, that's a bit of a
contradiction because we don't expect to
have occupation numbers way way way up
on the top. But those occupation numbers
which are non zero and non-negligible
will typically be proportional to n
itself. If you double the total number
of particles, the total number of boxes,
you will double the number of um of
boxes in each one of these uh
configurations. So by making capital n
big, we also make the little n's
big. Fun fact. Second, think of this
object over here as a function of the
little
ends. It's a highly peaked function.
We're not going to prove it. So, I'm
just going to tell it to you. When the
ends get very very very large, actually
I will wind up doing a a um a
calculation for you which will show you
this fact. But when the ins get very
very large if you were to think
of this quantity over here as a function
of the ends. Now the horizontal
axis stands for many horizontal axes
namely all the
ends. Typically this number here is a
very sharply peaked. I didn't draw it
sharply enough. as the ends get large,
it becomes a rather sharply peaked
function. So
that it doesn't fluctuate very much. It
doesn't fluctuate nearly as much as the
size of n itself.
That means when the number of boxes gets
very very big, you can be pretty sure
and as the number of boxes get bigger
and bigger, you can get shorer and
shurer
of what these little ends are. Now, more
specifically, that sounds a little
ridiculous. Uh, can I tell the
difference between having a box N1 with
5,271
uh occupation number versus
5,272? No, of course not. What I mean by
saying it's narrow is that it's narrow
on the scale of capital n itself. In
other words, that you can we're pretty
sure what the value of n subi over n
is that the ns don't fluctuate very
much. They are numbers get bigger and
bigger. They get tighter and tighter.
That means that for very very large
systems, these ends get pretty definite
or at least the
fractional ends become pretty
definite. All right, that uh that
suggests that we give them a name. The
fractional ends. Let's give the
fractional ends a name. Let's call
it P of
I. Why P? Well, if you have a large
number of identical
replicas subject to some
fluctuation, but you know the
ratio of the number of each type of box
to the total number, it makes a lot of
sense to think of that as the
probability that any given box is in the
state I. What is probability after all?
It's essentially the same thing as
saying you have a large number of
replicas of the same same thing and you
take the ratio between each given
outcome relative to the total number of
copies that you have and that's what's
called probability or at least that's
one way of representing probability. So
n subi over n can be thought of or at
least n subi over n
at the maximum up here the most likely
value of these occupation numbers they
can be identified with the probability
that any given box is in state I that's
the basic tool that uh that the it's as
simple as that more or less obvious So
we'll define p subi to be little n subi
/ n. And now let's rewrite the two
constraints that are up there. The two
constraints that are up there are first
of all the sum of n subi = n / capital
n. What does it become? It becomes the
sum of n subi / n is equal to 1 or
simply the familiar statement that the
sum of the
probabilities adds up to
one. Just divide through by n. And that
tells us the sums of the probabilities
add up to one. Not a big surprise. The
other statement, let's write it down.
summation over
I of N sub I E sub
I equals capital N times the average
energy in each box. I'll continue to use
the overbar notation for a little while
until I get tired of it. Now divide this
by capital N.
This becomes n subi / n and that's p
subi. The average in fact this is a much
more general formula than just for the
average energy. In general the average
of a quantity is the weighted sum over
the states of the system of the
probability of the i system times the
value of that quantity in the i state.
In this particular case, it's the
energy. So these two constraints or
those two constraints up there become
the very familiar.
Is that the total energy?
No, no, no, no, no, no, no. Okay, let's
go back over it again. It's not the not
the right hand side is not. We started
with sum of i n sub i e sub i is equal
to the total energy. But the total
energy is n * the energy of any box. Oh,
okay. And then we divided by capital n.
Okay. So I have gotten rid effectively
of the large number of boxes. But of
course the large number of boxes are
still in the problem here because
they're going to tell us it's the large
number of boxes and how they equilibrate
the energy between them that's going to
tell us what the uh what the energy
distributions what the piece of eyes
are. That's why I haven't told you what
the piece of eyes are.
Okay. So these are
constraints. Now what is the what are
the piece of eyes? The P sub eyes are
simply the values of the ends, not the
values of the ends, but the ratio, the
fractional value of the
ends at the most likely value of the
ends. In particular, if the system gets
very very big, it's extremely rare to
find yourself away from the uh the most
likely set of occupation numbers. And as
a system and as the system gets bigger
and bigger the ratio of these occupation
numbers gets more and more tightly
constrained to the to the value at the
maximum of this
function. So we then have to find the
maximum of pound here. I don't know when
I started calling it pound but a long
time ago.
uh the maximum of this thing as a
function of the ends subject to these
constraints can either be written this
way or the way on top. This is the
mathematical problem and it sounds like
a terrible mathematical problem but
fortunately it's extremely easy,
surprisingly
easy. It's a
um it's a couple of lines.
Let's now first thing to do, you don't
have to do what I'm going to do. There's
other ways to do it. I'm going to take
you through the most efficient procedure
uh which uh I didn't invent. It was
invented a long time ago. probably
people tried other procedures but the
most efficient procedure begins by
saying if you're maximizing
pound you can also substitute maximizing
its
logarithm. Why? If a function is
maximized at some point so is its
logarithm and the reason is because
logarithms are monotonic functions of
their arguments. So, we might as well
maximize it. The logarithm, why is the
logarithm interesting? We're going to
find out that the logarithm is
interesting because it's easier to work
with a sum than with a
product. Pound is a
product. The logarithm of it will be a
sum and that will that will help us
analyze it. So, what's the
logarithm of pound? The answer is the
logarithm of n factorial / the logarithm
of n1 sorry minus the logarithm of n1
factorial plus two factorial. In other
words, it's
just
log n
factorial minus the sum of the
logs of the n sub i
factorial. But now here the
simplification
happens when we use the sterling
approximation.
Sterling approximation is the trick that
makes all of this work and work out
beautifully. So let me remind you what
it is. Uh the sterling approximation can
be written in one of two ways. It can be
written as either n
factorial is approximately equal to n
the n eus
n or you can take its logarithm.
Incidentally, the if you did it
numerically, you would find out that
this is not all that accurate as n gets
big. But if you take this logarithm,
you'll find it's really accurate. The
logarithm of n factorial is equal to the
logarithm of n the n. That's n log
n minus r plus the logarithm of e the
minus the n. E to the minus N. The
logarithm of E to the minus N is just
minus
N. I think I proved this last time uh
by
by doing a little integral for you.
Yeah, we proved this last time or at
least at least motivated
it. And this is what we have here.
Logarithms of n factorial. And so we're
going to use the sterling approximation
in this
form. If you actually go and numerically
study these things, you find out that
this formula is very accurate. This one
not so accurate. This one's I mean you
know you take the thing which is pretty
accurate and you exponentiate it. Well,
you can you can flop around because of
the exponential. But but the logarithm
is a highly accurate
formula. When I say it's accurate, I
mean it becomes very very good for
large. the corrections to it get smaller
and smaller and larger. Okay. Um so
let's now substitute that into
here. We
have this equals log of n factorial
which is n to the
n. No. N log n
n log
n minus n. That's this term here. And
then we have minus the
summation of n sub i log n sub
i minus n sub
i. That's it. Let's work on it a little
bit. Let me take it over here. And I'm
going to take this piece of it over
here. Let's see. Do I want I want my
signs right? This one is plus. This
one's minus. This one's minus. And I
think this one's plus if I had I do it
right. Or I could put a bracket around
here. Minus. I put a bracket around
here. All right. Let's work on this
second term a little bit. The work that
I'm going to do with it is very simple.
I'm going to simply substitute that
n is equal to capital n * p for each
i. That's the same as saying n sub i
over capital n is p subi. I'm just going
to plug that into here and grind it
through. It's quite easy. So, let's take
the thing in the brackets. The thing in
the brackets then is equal
to each n subi that's replaced by n * p
sub i. So that's going to give me an
overall factor of
n. Each n subi will be proportional to
capital n be an overall factor of n and
then there will be a sum and the first
term and the first factor will be p of
i. All right, that's the n subi here.
Then we have logarithm of n sub i. So
that's logarithm
of p of i
*
n. That's this term over
here. And then we get to subtract
off
minus n subi. Incidentally, I left. No,
this is this is fine.
Um I think if I were really doing it
right, I would put a bracket over here.
Yeah. Summation n subi log n subi minus
summation n subi. Okay. So I won't
bother
writing. Yes, I won't bother writing
minus summation of n subi.
Okay. Just write P subi there. Yeah.
Where? On the end of the last enter. Oh,
I could write P subi there. You mean you
mean leave it through the factor of N
here? Yeah. Yeah, I could. Yeah, you're
right. Doesn't matter. But uh either
way, it'll uh the summation of so this
this piece the way I've defined it, this
piece does not multiply capital N. And
it doesn't matter. We could do it the
way you want. Also the summation of n
subi is capital n right okay so let's
replace this by minus capital
n and now
that that cancels this capital n
here right that one cancels this so I
think we can
safely replace This
this and ignore
that. Finish with
that. Now what about
this? Log of P * N is just log of P plus
log of N. So this becomes N * summation
of P of
I log P of
I. That's the first term. And then plus
sum sorry
n summation of
i of p of i
* log
n. See where that came from? The first
term is gotten by just taking the log of
p sub i. The second term is gotten by
replacing the log here just by log of n.
So that's
this. Now what's the sum of P sub I
one
which is pretty much what you would have
done if you would have done it the way
you said. All right. So this just goes
away and this gives us n log N. It comes
in with a minus sign and so it cancels
this N log in over
here. This thing is gone. All that's
left is this term over here with a minus
sign. The minus sign coming from here.
So the whole thing is just minus
n P of I log P of
I sorry log P of
I summed over
I. So if we know the if we had the
probability
distribution we would count well if we
had it probability it is just n piece
sub i log piece of body I now we've seen
this before anybody remember what it is
with a minus sign excuse me sign
entropy it is the
entropy it's n times the entropy which
appears
Yeah. Why did it come out n times the
entropy? Well, the reason it came out n
times the entropy is cuz there are n
boxes. But our problem, let's let's take
our mathematical problem. Now, our
mathematical
problem first of all has a minus sign in
it from
here. The number of ways of rearranging
things.
So the given of the logarithm of the
number of ways of rearranging things to
get a given set of occupation numbers is
just minus n * the sum of i p of i. This
is this kind of
way log p sub i. That's
it. Yes, you can remember that this is
the
entropy. But let's just take it for what
it is.
How can it possibly come out to be
negative? As long as it's negative.
Yeah. The log p subi is less than one
and so logarithm is negative. That's log
log. H. Yeah. Like
log ln same as log. Log is minus n* p
subi log p subi. And we want to maximize
this whole thing including the minus
sign. We want to maximize it. In other
words, we want to find out what little
ends give us the most likely
distribution of occupation numbers but
subject to two
constraints. The first constraint is
that the sum of the probabilities add up
to one.
So we have to remember that when we're
varying and trying to find the maximum
of this. We have to keep two things
fixed. We have to the sum of the P's
equal one and the sum of the P subi E
subi is equal to E. How do we do that?
Well, the answer is the method of
LR's
multipliers. All right, we add a lrange
multiplier for each
constraint and then later on afterwards
we figure out what the lrangee
multipliers have to be in order to make
the constraints actually satisfied. So
what we do then is we take this quantity
log of
pound and remember what is it a function
of in it's either you can think of these
are either as a function of the n sub
eyes or a function of the p sub eyes in
this problem the variables that we're
maximizing with respect to are these
probabilities themselves. We're trying
to find the most likely probability
distribution. So the p subi are the
unknowns and we're going to maximize
this
expression log of
pound
minus now we have to put in lrange
multipliers the first lrange multiplier
I will call
alpha that's the one that multiplies
this
constraint summation over i sub
i and the second lrange multiplier
I'll call beta minus
beta summation of i e sub i p sub
i. And we might as well now write in
what log of pound is. Here it is right
here. Oh, incidentally, one step that I
didn't we might as well throw away this
in. We're trying to maximize this
subject to some constraints. Well,
maximizing n times something is no no
different than maximizing the something
itself. Let's get rid of all n's. We
want to
maximize this thing right
here subject to the constraints that the
sum of the p's is one and the sum of the
e * p's is equal to e. So we
have sum of i p of
i
log p of i with a minus
sign plus no minus I think I chose the
lrange multiply to be minus here.
Now there's any questions up for now?
Yeah.
I I'm envisioning that most of the
native eyes are either zero or one
because uh the ones which are
appreciably non zero. Let's put it this
way. Okay, let's let's think of it the
following way. Um I think maybe it's it
will be helpful to pretend that there
is a highest energy would be of
proportional to yeah yeah but of course
of
course yeah but let's let's for
simplicity suppose that there is a
ceiling to the energy levels in other
words that there are a finite number of
these and then take capital n to be much
much bigger than the total number of
states that will make sure that every n
is
large. So the approximation here which
seems a little bit ridiculous but
nevertheless quite legal is to imagine
the number of replicas there is larger
than the number of
states and that's the approximation that
uh and it's it's not really an
approximation. It's just a useful uh uh
trick to keep in mind.
What of course is true is that the pace
subi go to zero as the energy gets very
very
large. Uh but uh we take that into
account by being very careful. The
easiest way to be careful is just to
truncate the energy levels at some
point. Yeah. Can you just say that when
the n subs are small that accounts for
very small part anyway? Yeah. Yeah.
Absolutely. Absolutely. Absolutely. So
um so that is not a problem but as I
said the easiest way to handle it
without with the least number of words
is just to say there's a maximum number
of states and capital N is much bigger
than
those but yes you're right that that is
correct that doesn't seem physical you
have just one particle in box it can go
10 million different have 10 million
states you have a number in a in a box
you got 10 million saves states times.
You could always make the number of
boxes bigger than the number of states
as long as the number of states is
bound. Now in practice the number of
states is bounded because you sure don't
want to have an energy in any one box
which is bigger than the total energy.
So in practice there is a bound but
uh uh but let's let's let's just uh take
it uh simply to say that there's an
upper bound here and capital n is much
bigger than that upper bound. That
simplifies simplifies the argument. All
right. The interesting thing is the
actual mathematical argument here. Now
notice all of these are sums over
i. There's no term in here, no single
term in here which involves more than
one p at a time. P sub 2 doesn't ever
get multiplied by P sub one. P sub one
gets multiplied by the logarithm of P
sub 1, but it doesn't get multiplied by
the logarithm of P sub 2. So this is a
function which is a sum of functions of
individual variables.
You maximize it by maximizing each
maximizing it for each I separately. How
do you maximize or what do you do next?
The next thing you do is you
differentiate this with respect to piece
of i or some this i is a summation
variable here. So let's not
differentiate with respect to p sub i.
Let's differentiate with respect to p
subj where j is some specific
number. P subj enters into one term
here, one term here and one term here. J
could be 46 or 59. It enters only into
one term of each of these. So when we
differentiate with respect to PJ, let's
do
it. First of all, the derivative the
derivative here is the sum of two terms.
One is the derivative of the first
factor times the second factor. That
will give us logarithm minus logarithm
of p of j.
I wonder if it helps to factor
pacers in all the
terms as a problem. We can take the
summation on the outside if that's what
you take the pi outside. No, no, no.
It's a sum over i. No, but I mean you
can't take the No, no.
You take you if you take the summation
on the outside.
Get rid of the sum here. Get rid of the
sum
here. Well, that's
it. You can't take the pi on the
outside. No, I'd say take the pi on the
outside of the parenthesis.
No. Well, yes. Oh, yes, you can
certainly take pi on the outside of the
parenthesis. Sure. Well, do it if you
like. I don't see that it helps
anything. Here it is. All right. So the
derivative of this term here has two two
fac two two terms. The first one is just
logarithm of pj. It's gotten by
differentiating this piece and the other
one
is minus the minus sign is all coming
from this overall minus sign on the
outside. So it's minus log piece subj.
And then what do we get from from the
differentiating log
1 p * p which is minus one.
Now what happens when we differentiate
this term with respect to pj?
We just get minus alpha.
And what happens when we differentiate
this term with respect to
PJ? We get minus beta *
EJ. And that all we set equal to zero.
That's the method
multipliers. Pretend that we're
minimizing this whole quantity with
respect to all of its variables.
So for each J we find that minus log of
PJ minus one plus alpha and so forth has
to add up to zero. I can throw away the
minus sign it appears in all of
them
minus plus
plus and now what do I have? I actually
have the probability distribution or
better yet or not better yet but it's
logarithm. So logarithm of
PJ
equals minus 1 + alpha that's from here
minus beta
EJ. Final step to go from the logarithm
of P to P itself we
exponentiate. Exponential of the left
hand side is PJ.
PJ
equ= e the minus 1 +
alpha times e to the
minus beta
ej. Now first of all look at this for a
little bit. This is just a number. Well,
it's a number that depends on the Lrange
multiplier, but it doesn't depend on
which state we're talking about. It
doesn't depend on J. All of the J
dependence, in other words, the
dependence on which state we're talking
about is all in this factor here. And
this tells us that the
probability of the J state is
proportional to E to the minus this
Lrange multiplier times the energy. It
tells us that the probability for
different energy levels falls off
exponentially as a function of the
energy. That's the basic property of the
Boltzman distribution. We did a bunch of
magic, a bunch of uh hand a slight of
hand, but all of it was good genuine
mathematics.
And we discovered that maximizing the
entropy subject to a constraint of a
given total probability and a given
total energy uniquely tells us that PJ
is proportional to E to the minus some
quantity time EJ. We're going to figure
out soon enough what beta is. I'll tell
you right now what theta is.
Beta is one over the
temperature or if I include Boltzman's
constant that's one over K * the
temperature. In most places when I write
one over temperature I really mean 1 /
KT.
uh in other
words for most
purposes I will set K equal to one and
work in units in which temperature has
units of of
energy. Okay. So beta then is actually
one over the temperature or proportional
to one over the temperature. But why
that's true we have yet to establish. We
have an independent definition of
temperature. If you go back in your
notes from the first time, there was an
independent definition of temperature
which I'll remind you of and we need to
establish that they're the same thing.
But for the time being, beta is a lrange
multiplier and we'll find out later that
it's one over the temperature. Now
um this object over here I'm going to
give another name. This is just naming
things. Now the lrange multiplier was
alpha but I'm going to give this whole
thing here another name. I'm going to
call it 1 / z. Why am I doing that?
Historical. It's a historical notation.
That's all. 1 / z. I can't help it. It
replaces the lrange multiplier. I don't
know what the lrange multiplier is yet.
I don't know what z is yet. I haven't
really done anything. I've just made a
change of notation. And this I'll leave
in this
form that may or may not be familiar to
you. Some of you who know a little bit
of statistical mechanics. This is a very
famous formula. For those who don't know
it, it's less
famous. All right. What is Z? When I say
what is Z, I mean what we should do now
is fix the lrange multipliers by making
sure that the constraints are satisfied.
Remember after solving the problem we
have to go back and say let's pick the
lrange multipliers so the constraints
are
satisfied. First constraint the sums of
the probabilities add up to
one. Let's see what that says.
The probability of the J state is 1 /
Z. And now we want the sum over all the
states. E to the minus beta. I'll now
use the P
subi. This is the sum
of what is this is the sum of P
subi. The sum I factored out the 1 / Z
from all of the terms. E to the minus
beta E sub I and the total probability
has to add up to
one. Well, just by multiplying by Z,
that tells us what Z is at least in
terms as a function of beta. In any
case, remember beta being temperature.
So, this gives us a formula for what Z
is. We still don't know what the
temperature is. We don't know what beta
is, but whatever beta is, that's equal
to Z.
And Z think of it as a function of beta
or as a function of
temperature. Z is called the partition
function. Again, very famous formula. Z
is defined by the sum. You take e to the
minus beta e sub i and you add it up for
all the energy levels and that defines
the partition
function. Knowing that that doesn't seem
like very much, the partition function.
It's one little piece of uh who cares
what the partition function is. It's
just a normalization factor that makes
sure your total probabilities add up to
one. Well, in fact, as we will see as we
go along, if you know the partition
function, you know everything. Partition
function as a function of the variables
of the problem is a way of codifying or
representing all the thermodynamic and
even beyond the thermodynamic
information all the statistical
information
uh in your system. So this is not only
an important function it contains
everything. So we'll see why. I don't
expect you to see why yet. All right.
How about beta? How do we choose beta?
The other constraint, the other
constraint is that the sums of the
probabilities times E subi has to add up
to the average energy. Now, I'm assuming
that we know the average
energy. The whole ensemble of copies had
a total fixed amount of energy. If I
just divide it by n, that tells me what
the energy of each replica is of each
copy. So I will assume for the moment
that I know what E is E bar or the
average energy of one uh one
copy. Let's write down the
formula. Summation over
I is again a one over Z on the outside.
That's because each P subi has a 1 / Z.
And then there is E to the minus beta E
sub
I. Okay, that's not finished. we have to
multiply by E
subi and that's equal to the average
energy. Now one it would be simple to
say look this does determine what beta
is. This is an equation for beta. I
already know what Z is in terms of beta.
So this is an equation if I know E bar.
This is a relationship between the
temperature if you like and the average
energy. But we can do a slick thing with
this. We can actually express all of
this nicely in terms of the partition
function itself. So let's see. Let's
find another blackboard here
and do
that. All
right, this is the object here whose sum
defines the partition function. But we
have an extra e subi here. The trick,
this is a trick, but this is such a
standard trick that by this point um
well, anybody who has done a little bit
of mathematics from time to time would
rather quickly realize that the next
step is to replace the e subi by the
derivative with respect to beta. If I
have a thing like e to the minus beta *
e and I want to multiply it any e and I
want to multiply it by e one way of
doing it is just to differentiate it
with respect to
beta and then we have to change the
sign. The derivative with respect to
beta of an exponential e to the minus
beta e is just e times the exponential
not this e
this is equal to e
* e to the minus beta
e. All right. So every place here where
you see e * eus beta e let's write it as
1 /
z sum on
i derivative with respect to beta. So
I'm going to write it as partial
derivative with respect to beta. The
reason is later on not now but later on
there are going to be more variables in
the problem. volume, magnetic field, all
sorts of things. And I mean
differentiate all those other things
fixed. For our purposes here, I could
just use ordinary
derivatives. But later on, we we'll want
to remember there may be more variables
in the problem. And now I mean
differentiating the beta keeping all the
other things in the problem fixed
of e to the minus beta e sub i
period. Now
minus
sign. Now the derivative can be taken
outside the sum. The sum of derivatives
is the derivative of the sum. All right.
So the derivative can be taken out on
the outside. Let's take it on the
outside. It becomes d by d
beta of the
sum. And what is this? This is the
partition function. So we have a lovely
formula
now that the average
energy is equal to
minus 1 upon Z derivative of Z with
respect to
beta. Beta remember is the inverse
temperature. So again if you know the
partition function as a function of
beta then here it is z of
beta then all you have to do is
construct 1 / z * the derivative of z
with respect to beta at that temperature
that will give you the average energy.
This gives you a relationship between
average energy or just energy let's call
it and the temperature. The right hand
side is a function of temperature. The
left hand side is the average energy.
This can be rewritten as minus the
derivative of logarithm of Z with
respect to
beta. 1 / Z by D beta is derivative of
logarithm of Z. A logarithm of Z occurs
over and over and over
again. And it occurs so much that we
give it a special name.
That's the average energy.
Oh, before we talk about the the the
name of this thing, let's just see what
it says. The left hand side is a
well-defined I mean if we can calc to
the extent that we can calculate Z of
beta. It's a function of beta and a
function of beta is equal to the energy.
We can invert that and we can find out
what beta is as a function of the
energy. Whatever that relationship is,
if we can invert it, we can find out
beta as a function of the energy. Beta
is the lrange
multiplier, but it is also the inverse
temperature. So this is the relationship
between temperature and
energy. In many examples, we actually
won't want to invert this. We may know
the temperature in which case we may be
more interested. We know the
temperature. We may be more interested
in finding the energy. In some cases we
may know the energy and we may be
interested in finding out what the
temperature is at that at that uh that
energy. This
formula together with the formula that Z
is summation of E to the minus beta E
subi G of
beta that as I said contains a good deal
of information more than a deal endless
amounts of
information about the statistical
system.
Uh let's see what we
got. Yes, I told you that logarithm of Z
has a special
name. Let me just get the signs right.
Um,
Nick T, temperature logarithm of Z with
a minus sign, which is the same as
logarithm of Z / beta. Anybody know what
that's called?
with a minus sign.
Before I tell you before I tell you its
name, let's just notice Z is not itself
actually a single exponential but it
sort of looks like an exponential of
beta* energy. If I take the logarithm of
Z, I expect it to be to have at least
have units or be similar to beta times
some kind of thing that I might call a
thing which has units of
energy. Uh so the logarithm of Z is sort
of like what's up here. It's not really,
but I mean it's sort of like the sort of
thing which goes in the exponent here.
And if I divide it by
beta, then it's some kind of thing which
has units of
energy. The logarithm of Z divided by
beta has units of energy. Of course,
really Z is the sum of such terms. But
that doesn't prevent us from calling
this kind of
energy. It is what it is. It is not the
energy of the system. It's the Helmholtz
free energy. It's called A is the Helm
Holtz free
energy as units of energy and it's just
minus the logarithm of Z / beta. Why
minus the logarithm? Because the
exponential here carries a minus with
it. So it's natural to put a minus in
front of
it. All right. So that's and that's
definition. There's no
uh no proof of that. That's the
definition of
a the helmhold's
free. Okay. What is not
definition is a
relationship between the energy the
helmhold's free energy and the entropy.
We've defined entropy already.
uh we certainly know what energy is and
we now have a definition of the
Helmholtz uh free energy. There is a
relationship between the three of these
things energy, entropy and Helmholtz
free energy which we should derive. It's
easy enough to derive.
Um you might be saying to yourself by
this point already, when the hell are we
going to get to molecules and
gas? The answer is pretty soon.
But it is worth exploring the general uh
the general mathematics before we do
particular systems. Once we have some
mathematics in place once we know and
understand how to use this partition
function as a generator of all kinds of
answers we will have a machine that we
can mindlessly use to crank out all
kinds of things about statistical
mechanical systems. So it's worth
exploring the general principles before
we actually try to attack the system. Uh
let's just see what we uh let's see we
have free energy is equal to logarithm
of z / beta and let me just write down
next to it here the energy itself that
was not by definition but by calculation
was equal to minus the derivative of the
logarithm of with respect to
beta. They're kind of similar. One is
actually the logarithm of Z / beta and
the other is the derivative of a
logarithm of Z with respect to beta.
They're not the same thing, right? If Z
well, you can see that they're not the
same thing, but uh they have some
relationship to each other. If Z if
logarithm of Z was a straight line,
which it is in general not, but if it
were a straight line as a function of
beta, then they would be the same. But
of course they're not uh it's not a
straight
line. But those are the two important
quantities. And one more quantity is the
entropy. So let's calculate the entropy.
And we're going to find that the entropy
is closely
related to A and E and of course theta.
What is the entropy? The entropy is
minus the sum of p sub i logarithm of p
sub
i. But now we know what p sub i is. We
know that it's just up there 1 / z e to
the minus beta ej e
r piece of i. So let's plug that in and
grind away and calculate what the
entropy is. Maybe we'll get stuck and we
won't be able to do it in any useful or
interesting way. We can just do the sum
of course but maybe we'll get somewhere.
So let's try it. S is equal to minus.
Now what's p subi?
1 /
z is a sum on the
outside 1 / z * e to the
minus beta e sub
i. And now what's the logarithm of p sub
i? It's the logarithm of that expression
up there except change j to i. The
logarithm of that is
minus
beta e sub
i. That's the logarithm of the second
factor, the exponential. And then we
have to subtract off minus log
z. Okay. Does everybody see what I've
done? I've written P subi as 1 / Z eus
beta e sub i and then logarithm of p sub
i
as minus beta e sub i minus log
z that's
s the minus sign goes
away taking a minus sign the overall
minus minus sign and the minus signs
here and cancel them. Okay, what's the
first term? 1 / z eus beta e sub i *
beta e subi. Suppose the beta wasn't
there first. That's the average
energy. That's the average energy. So we
can say that s is equal the first term
is just the average energy times beta.
Sorry, times beta. That's this beta over
here. And what about the second term?
The second
term there's no I dependence in here.
This is just logarithm of Z. It's that
doesn't depend on I at all. So in doing
the sum here, all we're doing is summing
E to the minus beta E subi. What is
that? Sum of E minus beta E subi
Z and that cancels the Z here. So all
we're left with is logarithm of Z plus
log of
Z. Go over that
again. Let's we've taken care of the
first term here. That was just the
average energy. The second term we can
factor out no sorry we can factor out
the log of Z on the outside. It's log of
Z. And then it's just the sum of 1 / Z E
minus beta E subi. That's just
one. That's just one. So that's it. What
do we have? We now have a formula
relating
entropy energy and home holds free
energy. The helmhold's free energy let's
uh I don't want to erase it in this
form. Let's just put it up here. And
again logarithm of Z is minus beta * A.
So here we have it. S is equal to beta
* E minus A.
So the helmhold's free
energy or the difference the difference
between the energy and the helmhold's
free energy is just the
entropy or the entropy uh divided by
beta. Another way we can write it by
using that beta is one over temperature.
We can write it as t
ss is equal to e minus
a. So whatever the helm holds free
energy is the difference between it and
the real energy is just or
the average energy is just temperature
times
entropy. This allows us to express the
entropy in terms of the partition
function. Let's see what it is. We have
to take e minus a. So e minus a
is well it's the logarithm of z /
beta minus derivative of the log of z
with respect to
beta. This is what the entropy is. This
is a formula for the entropy. I don't
mean this is not the definition of the
entropy. A and that's equal to T S. Do I
have that
right? If I'm lucky, the temperature
will cancel from this one. Yeah, this is
also one over
beta. All right. So, we can multiply by
beta if we like. Multiply by beta.
Another form S is equal to log
Z minus beta d log
Z by D
beta whole bunch of formulas. The main
upshot main upshot is when you know
Z you have tools for calculating energy
entropy helm holds free energy if it
means anything to you which it will
because we will use it for all sorts of
applications. Uh thus far I haven't told
you what it's good
for other than calculating the entropy
from the energy but you can see that
there's some power in knowing the
partition function. Each one of the
various thermodynamic variables can be
represented fairly easily in terms of
the logarithm of Z. It's always the
logarithm of Z which comes into things.
So the logarithm of Z is um often more
interesting than Z
itself
question. Yeah, we haven't we haven't um
the way to demonstrate it or something.
What's that? You have to compute like a
variance or something. Yeah, it's a
variance. Okay, let's good this. I was
going to jump into the uh the uh uh
ideal gas, but let's before we do that,
let's do
variances, statistical fluctuations, and
see if we can
uh learn something about the size of
statistical fluctuations.
What we'll find is that they're very
small. But let's uh let's let's see if
we do
that. We have a choice now either to
jump into a an application which is
theory of gas uh and so forth or to do a
little more theory. The more theory
being theory of
fluctuations and the theory of
fluctuations is sort of general theory.
The theory of gases is a special case.
Which would you rather do? Theory.
Fluctuations. I mean, it's it's awfully
interesting.
Uh, so so are gases, but less general.
All right, let's do
fluctuations. Let's take a
quantity. Let's call it
X. X is of course a thing which has a
value for each state of the system. For
each state of the system, X has some
value.
And I'm interested in the probability
distribution. I'm interested in the
variance of X or if you like. Let's call
it the uncertainty or the fluctuation of
X. The fluctuation in X. How do we
define it? Well, I'll give you a
definition. The definition is first of
all subtract from X its average. So
subtract from
X its average value.
So if we have a probability distribution
for X which looks like that we subtract
the average value which is in here
somewhere and that effectively just
moves the probability distribution so
that the center of the probability
distribution or the average of the
probability distribution is now located
at
zero. Other than that
uh and Xbar does not depend on I. It's
just a number. it uh just a number. Now
we take this and we square
it and then we take the average of the
whole
thing. So we have some probability
distribution which is centered at the
origin and center at the origin because
I've shifted it.
We take x^2 and we average it and that
gives us the that is a measure of the
width of the distribution. It's always
positive because it's a square of
something and when averaged it's always
positive and it measures the width of
the distribution. All right. You call
that the
variance mean square
uh root mean square something or other.
Yeah. Okay. So that's the statistical
variance in X and I want to calculate it
for well first of all let me simplify it
or let me reexpress it first of all this
can be expressed as the average
incidentally the overbar and the bracket
notation are the same thing I just
didn't want to write brackets inside
brackets all right so what is this first
of all let's take the thing inside the
bracket it's
x squared
- x *
xr + xr^
2 if you like call this x sub i x of
i and now we have to average this first
of all what's the average of x sub i
squar well it's just the average of x^2
so this here is just the average of x²
square first term. What about the
average of XAR
squared? It's just X bar squared. Xar
doesn't depend on I. It's just a number
as far as I is concerned. And averaging
a number is just the number. So this
gives us plus Xar^
squared. Now notice I'll deal with this
one in a moment, but notice this is not
the same as this.
This is the average of the square. This
is the square of the average. Okay, two
different things. The square of the
average, the average of the square. And
now what about this one? What's the
average of this?
It's just min
-2 xar xar xar 2. Averaging x gives us
xar and it just multiplies this xar. So
it's - xr^ 2. Two of these one over
here. The result is just
x this one squared
minus this
one. All right. So this is a standard
statistical fact that the variance in a
variable is the difference between the
average of the square and the square of
the average. If I want to write it in a
single notation, I will write it this
way. The difference of the average of
the square and the square of the
average. That's the variance. For a
narrow
distribution, when the distribution is
narrowly peaked, this is
small. Smaller it is, the narrower the
distribution. So, let's try to
calculate. Let's see how smart we can be
and see if we can calculate the variance
in uh in the
energy. Try to calculate the variance in
the
energy. What would it mean incidentally
for the distribution to be sharply
peaked? It would mean that the variance
in the energy is much smaller than the
energy
itself or is I guess we would call this
the square of the variance. You call
this the variance or the square of the
variance.
But it's also the square of the
uncertainty in X if you like. It's the
square of the width of the distribution.
So we might want to compare this
quantity here with the square of the
energy itself. In other words, we might
want to compare the difference of these
two to either one of them separately.
When that's small, we say that the peak
is sharp. But let's see how well we can
do how far can we go in calculating this
variance for
energy. We've calculated the average of
the energy. Let's write down the
formula. The average there it is right
here. But let me write it over here. The
energy is equal to minus d log
z with respect to
beta. Let's see if we can calculate the
average of the square of the
energy. This is the average energy. Now
I'm going to use the fact that it really
was the average of the
energy. Most of the times I
I don't bother writing this average but
this is the average of the energy.
minus b log
z we'll wind up squaring it because
we're instructed to square it over here
but first let's calculate the average of
the square of the energy so for that we
need a formula for this average of the
square of the square of the energy is p
of i * e sub i
squar that's the average of the square
of the
energy which is equal
equal to 1 /
Z sum e minus beta e sub i that's p sub
i * e sub i^
2 remember what I did to find the
average energy I just in that case we
only had one power of energy here we
just differentiated with respect to beta
to bring down that e here what should I
do to you get the e^2 second take the
second derivative when I take the second
derivative you'll find
out that the average of
e^2 is just 1 /
z times the second derivative of
z with respect to beta squar
correct I think now there's no minus
sign
is it z or Z
uh
Z Z E Z E Z E Z E Z E Z E Z E Z E Z E Z
E Z E² it gives you two derivatives.
Okay, z^2. Okay, now we can write down
the variance. The variance is first of
all this term 1 /
z d z by d beta
squ and now we have to
subtract the average of e^ 2 which is
minus d
log of z by d beta
squared. In fact, let me write this
slightly differently. Uh, the log z by d
beta is 1 / z dz by d beta. So, actually
this is just 1 / z
^2 1 / z ^2 dz by d beta 1 z ^2 dz by d
beta 1 / z dz by d beta
squ. So it's the difference between 1 /
z * the second derivative of z with
respect to beta minus 1 / z ^2 dz by d
beta^ 2. That's the
variance. We're not finished with it
yet. This is simpler than it
looks. That's right.
This is I
believe I think it's just the second.
Let's try it out. The second derivative
of log
z with respect to beta is I think what
it
is. Let's try it out and find
out the derivative of log z with respect
to theta. Let's see.
um derivative of log z with respect to
beta
that's 1 /
z dz by d
beta that's the first derivative and now
we want to differentiate it again with
respect to
beta right so what happens when we
differentiate this product here with
respect to beta I get one term which is
1 / z * the second der derivative of Z
with respect to
beta that's
here. Now what's the other term when I
differentiate 1 / Z with respect to
beta? That gives me 1 - 1 / z ^2 another
factor two factors of dz d beta is that
clear when I differentiate to get this
sphere for a moment let's put it over
here dz by d
beta when I differentiate 1 / z with
respect to beta I get minus 1 / z^²
another dz by d
beta and so that gives me this term
here. So, here's what I found. I found
out that the
um that the variance is just the second
derivative of log z with respect to
beta. Okay, let's uh let's examine it a
little more closely.
the log z by d
beta that's equal to minus the
energy. So what this whole thing is I
mean we've made a number of steps. I
whenever I do this I always feel like
I've done too many
steps like I've done the same steps
backward and forward and back. Yeah.
Would you not mind giving a physical
interpretation of
Z as to what Z I know
it's part of the solution alpha for the
but
this is not a constant no it's a
function of beta it's function
and whatever it is it contains all the
information about the thermodynamics
it's a thing which you differentiate you
take its logarithm you do all sorts of
tricks with it and it generates the full
thermodynamics. Uh what can I tell you?
It's proportion. It's free energy or
it's logarithm is the free energy. It's
logarithm divided by beta. Um we're
going to calculate these things over and
over and eventually you'll get some
sense for what it is. But I there's no
is it an intermediate type
of variable? It's a generating function.
It's a generating function that
generates lots of answers. You do things
to it. Um, you know what it
is? Um, it's the applause transform of
what is it? The applause. Uh, it's the
applause transform of the density of
states. Does that help you at all?
It doesn't have a simple interpretation,
something you can measure. It's
something you do something to to
generate uh to generate answers, right?
The action in mechanics is a thing that
you do things to to generate equations
of motion and so forth. The partition
function is also a generating function
that you do various operations and just
about everything you can think of in
thermodynamics and and in fluctuations
take us beyond thermodynamics.
H
what are the units of Z? Say it again.
The units of Z. Z is
dimensionless. Z is dimensionless. Um
things in exponents are always
dimensionless. So when you sum things in
exponents, it's always dimensionless. So
it has
been I would say rather than saying what
its physical interpretation is which
means I suppose that means how does it
relate to measurable quantities is it a
measurable quantity no it's not in
itself directly a measurable quantity
it's not what it's physical
interpretation is it's what you can do
with it to generate things whose
physical interpretation you do you do
Okay. So we'll uh we'll we'll play with
it a lot. But in any case, we've now
seen that we can calculate the
fluctuations in the energy as well as
the energy
itself. Uh but let's uh let's do a
little more with it. We're calculating
the I guess I could call it the the
fluctuation in energy squared. Let's
think of it that way. The uncertainty or
the spread in the energy squared. And
what we find out is that it's the second
derivative of log z with respect to beta
squ. All right. Now the first derivative
of log z is just the energy minus
minus the energy. And so we have d by d
beta of the
energy. Now what is beta? Beta is one
over temperature. So this can be related
to the derivative of the energy with
respect to temperature. This is D
E D
beta which is D E by DT
temperature D temperature D
beta but beta is just one over
temperature. So what's the what's the dt
d beta
1 t^2 right minus 1 over t^2
no t square uh t^² t^2 t by d beta let's
write that out um t is equal to 1 / beta
dt by d
beta is equal to minus 1 / beta^
2 which is equal to minus t ^2 square.
Okay.
So, did I lose a minus sign?
Here it is. The key by the d
beta is just minus that gets rid of a
minus and this becomes t ^2
upstairs. Now, what is this d e by dt?
It's got a name. The second the heat
capacity.
It's the heat capacity. The heat
capacity d by
dt is the heat
capacity. It's definition of heat
capacity. It's the amount of
well amount of energy accumulated amount
of energy to change the temperature by
one unit. Okay. How much energy do you
have to put in to change the energy by
one unit? Um
could we go back just a second here?
Yes. Oh, we showed that the delta E^2 is
the second derivative of log Z with
respect to
beta^ okay now where do we get how do we
get the first derivative is just the
energy right the log z by d beta apart
from the sign the log z by d beta is
energy so the answer is the derivative
of energy with respect to beta
Yeah. Log Z with Okay. So I see what
you're saying. The equation.
Yeah. The first derivative just beta.
Right. Now I want to differentiate this
again with respect to beta. So it's just
d by d e by d beta
which if I decide I would like to use
temperature instead of just for
familiarity sake if I like temperature
better than beta which I do I'm going to
sense of temperature I substitute uh the
e d beta d beta dt and it gives me t ^ 2
times the specific heat not the specific
heat
uh I always say specific heat when I
mean
heat capacity t
^2 times the heat
capacity.
Okay, first of all, how does the heat
capacity grow with the number of
particles in a
system? Remember what it is now or the
or the size of the system? Let's say the
number of
particles. It's the amount of heat that
you need to change the temperature by
one unit that's proportional to the
number of particles in the
system. The bigger the system, the
heavier the system, the more energy you
have to put in to change the temperature
by a given amount. And in fact, the heat
capacity is proportional to the mass of
the system depending on uh what you use.
Let's just say the number of particles
in the system. So the right hand side
here is proportional to the number of
particles. What about the energy
itself also proportional to the number
of particles? But the square of energy
is what we should compare it with is the
square of the energy has the units of
squares of energy. The square of the
energy is proportional to the square of
the number of particles. So in that
sense the fluctuation is very much
smaller than the energy itself. We
should take the square root of both
sides in order to have a fluctuation in
the energy. The uncertainty in the
energy is t * the square root of the uh
the heat capacity. Heat
capacities grow linearly with the number
of particles in a system.
So this idea grows like the square root
of the number of particles but the
energy
itself grows linearly with the number of
particles. So the fluctuation divided by
the quantity
itself gets smaller and smaller like 1
divided by the square root of the number
of
particles. That's the demonstration if
you like that fluctuations are small by
comparison with the quantities
themselves. So that's one way of seeing
it. Um I might also add one more
point. Let's keep track. I rarely keep
track of Boltzman's constant. Okay? But
let's keep track of Boltzman's constant
a little
bit. In order to keep track of
Boltzman's constant, I'll give you some
standard.
Let's call them undergraduate textbook
definition. According to the standard
undergraduate textbook definition, I'll
call it temperature little t
uh and little t is such that it times
the boltsman
constant is what I call big
t. That's the definition of boltz or if
you like that's that's where the
boltsman constant comes in. and also the
standard
undergraduate textbook definition of
entropy which I will call little S. You
also multiply that by K bolts to get
what I call big
S. What I call
entropy. No decent information theoretic
physicist would ever define anything
except this except if you're trying to
compare things to a definition of
entropy which was in some ancient
textbook. Then you would put a K bolt in
there. Notice that K boltzine will
cancel out. Let's see. Do I have this
right? Equals. Do I have this upside
down?
Um KT is what I call temperature.
Uh well, let's
see. The E=
TS.
Um which should equal little T d little
S.
So I think I have this upside down. I
think it's K bolt of
denominator. Yeah, I think that's
right. This is standard textbook
definition and it's such that when you
write that the E equals TDS, it's the
same as writing it in the uh in the
undergraduate textbook sense. The K
volts means cancel. Just engineer the
definition of entropy so that they
cancel out of
the t * s the volts. Yeah, that that's
correct. Use a standard definition. It's
very hard to prove that the that beta is
one over t.
Uh we're going to do it at some point.
It's in the notes and we're going to do
it. But uh at the moment, let it be a
definition. Okay. Yeah. Uh well, that's
a definition, but uh we this is this was
also a definition. We have two
definitions. They could clash. They
don't. Okay. So, yeah, we'll do that,
but not now.
Um, right now, let's go back to this
formula over here that the uncertainty
in the energy
squared is equal to P ^2 times the heat
capacity, which is what? It's D by DT.
Does this formula make dimensional
sense?
Uh well, it does make yeah it makes
dimensional sense. But where does the
Boltzman constant go into this? Um the
answer is wherever you see capital T and
you want to use let's call it
undergraduate physics notation put K *
little T. So that means that we can put
little t here, little t squared, little
t here, and then I think there's one k
boltzman in the in the numerator
here. This is in fact the first place in
anything we've discussed where k
boltzman actually appears. K boltzman
appears in
fluctuations. This is the heat capacity.
It's a thing you measure in the
laboratory. It's neither terribly small
nor terribly big. It's just uh whatever
energy it how much how much uh heat, how
many BTUs or how many
uh calories or how many jewels you have
to pump in to change the temperature by
a certain amount. So this is neither a
terribly small quantity nor a very big
quantity. This temperature could be room
temperature 300° or whatever. It's also
not a very big number or a small number.
We do expect for a big box of gas for a
mole of gas for example we expect the
fluctuations in energy to be very small
at least by comparison with the energy
itself. Here's another source of
smallness. K voltman is a very small
number. How small? 10us
23rd. All right. So this number is 10 -
23rd 1.4 * 10 - 23rd or something like
that. And so this tells us for a mole of
gas the fluctuations in the energy at a
reasonable temperature are very very
small for among for no other reason
because K Bzman appears in the in the
formula.
So yeah fluctuations are small
probability distributions are highly
peaked when the number of particles
becomes large.
That's not the same C as the other one.
Yeah it was. I think uh well the other
one was eaten by the big Oh, you're
right. Uh so what
K?
No, KB KB shouldn't cancel.
Um
I don't think it should.
Oh, right.
Yeah.
The EDT, the LD² is equal to DT * T ^ 2,
right?
Um, KBT.
Let's let's put T here and that would
put a KB here, right? Yeah. And then P
^2 would be P ^2 * KB 2, right? Yeah.
You have the right thing. It's just that
what you wrote C as equal to is the E by
D.
Oh, you you're right. The standard
definition of heat capacity is DE by D
little T. All right. So, you're right. I
was careless. Okay. So, here we have it.
Two KBs in the numerator, 1 KB in the
denominator. And this is the thing that
you would normally call capacity, the E
by D little T. Okay. Right. Good. Thank
you. Very good. All right. So, we see
two two senses in which first of all,
it's got a numerical constant in front
of it which is very small. But in the
second sense, it's also true that the um
the fluctuation in energy only grows as
the square root of the number of
particles whereas the energy itself
typically grows as the part number of
particles itself.
That's characteristic of course of a
fluctuation growing as square root of
the quantity that's the fluctuation
up. That's the sense in which the
probability distribution is
narrow.
Um well let's see. I think uh I think
that's a good place to stop. I I really
have
Oh, we have 15 more minutes.
Um, the next time we're going to go into
the theory of the ideal gas and not so
ideal gas and do some things with it.
But uh let me
just No, I think we're going to stop.
Yeah, let's stop and feel some
questions. And if there are no
questions, uh yeah, I think we should
begin leave a little bit early today
because I didn't get my cookie.
I had a dog and pony show with the
bankers today. Yeah.
My wife who doesn't know anything about
computers gets very very annoyed when a
computer something's happening and says
your cookie has been
deleted. I also don't know what a cookie
is but I don't get so annoyed I
know my cookie was
deleted. Okay. Uh if there are no
questions other question I have one
question from last you said the the
quantities that are conserved like
charge they actually the total quantity
of the universe is zero and oh well
that's when yeah okay I did say that
last week I think he said the same thing
with energy yes so where's negative in a
closed in a closed universe
okay in a closed universe so I see all
sorts of positive energy I don't see any
negative energy
No, the negative
energy is a dot over a squared
term in the uh expansion of the
universe. It's the uh it's the kinetic
energy of expansion space. Yeah. And
it's purely got to do with um geometry.
It's the expanded geometry of space. And
it's the term that uh corresponds to the
gravitational energy.
Gravitational grav the energy stored in
the gravitational field. Okay. And the
gravitational field is geometry. In this
case the geometry is fourdimensional
geometry. Geometry is spatial geometry
is expanding. That means the
fourdimensional geometry is something
that looks like that. Okay. Expanding.
It's not flat. It's not good flat space.
It has some energy of its own and uh
that's the and that's and that's associ
associated with gravitational fields
associated with
gravitational. If all the other energies
are positive then it forces the universe
to expand.
Yeah.
What about information? You were saying
that was more fundamental, but it seems
like all the information of all the
bubbles was in this one at the
beginning. All the information in what?
For all the bubbles in the ent term of
inflation. Oh yeah. Yeah. We getting are
we going in there?
Let's not go there now. I'm too
hungry. Somebody wanted to ask me a
question about the lecture
uh from
uh you wanted to ask a question about uh
Alex's lecture about the Lincoln's
lecture.
Oh, that was that
question. He said that that the total
energy was zero. Another thing is he the
argument for closed universe where the
total be it sort of all the lines of
force came back. Yeah. Why doesn't that
work for mass? It's said we have a
closed universe. Mass is energy.
Okay. So you would have gravitational
lines and would they not all converge
the same way that they No, you have to
keep in mind that there's also there's
all that there's a a gravitational
component to the energy that's not uh
there's only one conservation law. It's
energy. Mass is a is not conserved in
relativistic physics. Mass itself is not
conserved. Only I say there's only one
conservation law. There are many
conservation laws but energy and mass
are not separate conservation laws.
Right. Right. In my general context it's
just energy and energy has various
components in addition to all the usual
stuff which by itself is not
conserved in an expanding universe. The
ordinary components of the energy are
not conserved.
uh and the non-conservation is
compensated for by a change in the
gravitational energy. That's this. Okay.
Yeah. So you can either say that in
general relativity there's no concept of
conservation of energy or you can keep
track of pieces of the energy which are
a little
unfamiliar and then you would say not
only is it conserved but it's exactly
zero. Okay.
Didn't he say the cosmic horizon?
Uh, he's probably more accurate than I I
was. Earlier time that things are now 40
billion lighty years away universe
still. Okay. Yeah. Uh, he's probably
good. Yeah, he's probably more accurate.
15 was an order of magnitude within a
factor of three. Yeah. No, I I I'm sure
he's right. I I didn't uh I didn't sit
down and calculate it.
I think basically the difference is
there some expansion since the light
that's furthest away.
Yeah, that's that's what
makes a basic understanding of this
multimate distribution.
distribution. Yes. Increase energy. If
you increase, let's see.
Okay. PJ.
It seems that the lowest energy state is
always going to have the highest. Yes,
it does. So what we have is this long
tip that gets longer as the energy the
ground state is the one that
has okay right that that is correct
um that is correct so let's let's put
let's put in over
here at very very low temperatures the
probability distribution is is sort of
squashed toward very low energy As the
temperature goes up and you go to
enormously high temperatures, what
happens? What happens? And these are of
course the states. These are all
states.
The distribution gets flat. All states
become equally probable at infinite
temperature. At infinite temperature,
that's a state of absolute maximum
entropy that you can possibly have.
Infinite temperature. You know nothing
about the system. So all all are right.
Now there's another element here. The
typical states of a system are not
equally spaced like this. If you were to
write not state number here I but energy
you would find out that the low energy
states are fairly well separated from
each other and they get denser and
denser and denser and denser and denser.
So if you ask about the probability for
a given energy, not the probability for
the I state, you would find out that
tilts it toward higher energies because
there are just more states with higher
energy. There are many many more states
with higher energy than there are with
lower energy. So if you wanted to
know what the probability is that the
energy is between two limits here, you
would have to say two at a given
temperature. You would take the
probability that you're in the E state
and multiply it by the number of states
in that narrow bin and that narrow bin
gets more and more states. You
understand what I'm saying?
You get more what? You get more
there are more states. There are more
states of within a given range of
energy. Let's say within a given range
of energy delta E over
here and delta E over here. There are
just many many more states here than
there are here.
More more things. It depends on what
you're plotting. If you're plotting the
probability for the I state
then it's just flat. But if you're
calculating the probability for a given
energy, then it's tilted up.
Can you ever have a system where you get
a different kind of distribution where
you figure
out everything?
You mean
you're asking whether there's any
interesting situations where the
probability let's plot here the E state,
not the energy itself, where the
probability distribution might look like
that. Well, it won't be equilibrium.
Okay, it won't be
equilibrium. Um, it won't be equilibri,
but you can see from this
incidentally why it is that both the
energy and the entropy increase
monotonically with temperature. What
happens as temperature increases? At low
temperatures, the distribution looks
like that. At higher temperatures, the
distribution gets spread. As higher
temperatures, the distribution get
spread. It's completely obvious the
average energy
grows. But why does the average entropy
grow? Remember what entropy is? It's the
width. It's the average number of states
contained within the distribution. As
the distribution gets flatter and
flatter, it contains more states with
significant probability. So both the
entropy and the energy are typically
monotonically increasing functions of uh
of um of the temperature. Temperature
goes up, energy goes up, entropy goes
up. Isn't laser an example of uh a
situation you get that kind of oation
inversion?
Yes. And in those cases you get negative
temperature. We can talk about that next
time. Uh yeah. Yeah. But of course if
you take the the laser really isn't a
system in thermal equilibrium where
there's environment and everything else.
It's a uh uh but yes the answer is yes
question about the EI. The EI is some
number proportional to I assume. Is that
correct? What do you mean proportional
to I? Proportional you mean linear? Yeah
because I mean you numerous.
Well, these these states are not really
equally spaced like that in and what
determines how they're how they're
spaced the system
itself mechanical particle in a box
would have a level density which
denser and denser. Okay. No, I mean
that's something you have to know what
the system is. That's that's a
characteristic. The system is
hydrogen. I can tell you what the answer
for. All right. Well, I will tell you
now what another
way. The answer is that the density of
states the density of
states usually called row of E is the
number of states per unit
energy. It's the number of states. Let's
call it delta N / delta E. This is
number of states.
That's e to the
entropy.
Uh that's but we we haven't proved that
but that's a fact that uh that uh e to
the entropy is the density of states for
most systems. And so since entropy is an
increasing function of energy, the
density of states is also typically an
increasing function of uh
so so for a gas then would have some
characteristic distribution. Oh yeah
yeah yeah we'll calculate that
distribution.
It's equivalent to calculating the
entropy. That's not obvious it is true.
question. Did did Boltzman actually
postulate that there was some sort of
fundamental side of energy? Did he
assume that there was a continuous? No,
he assumed there was a continuous spect.
So, it's a little different, is there?
Yeah. Uh, a little bit, but we're going
to get into that next time. Next time we
will have to talk uh we're not going to
be thinking about quantum mechanics. We
will have to talk about what happens
when the energy distribution is
continuous. Okay.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.